this is a really interesting one that I
want to go through through sort of
carefully it's another place there are
two places where jetone copy himself
uses this quotation so I thought you
might like to hear that and uh it
happens to be from a secret text but I'm
just going to do a little piece so it
doesn't matter
uh let's suppose somebody has completed
did their King practice okay and in
their Zing practice they've got up to
se which is a certain part of higher
tantic
practice they didn't do the three
activities which we'll talk about
later
uh but at the moment of their
death they they are able to link into
the clear light of death
which is uh Ultimate
Reality direct uh sorry they're able to
to link into that he doesn't say
directly necessarily but anyway
Shar then when they die at the end of
the death
processa they should think them
themselves I want to enter an angel's
body I want to enter an angel's body
okay
patang patang means what
make make that resolution it's like
decide that that's what you want to be
then
she what then die okay sheina okay if
you do that says Jona this is all secret
stuff that's
okay then you will go through the
various stages of death you will enter
the clear light of death
and
then then in the next in the in the next
few minutes in the time that other
people would be entering
B like the scary place between death and
rebirth
right instead of that uh do means this
do means as a replacement for that okay
they do like G Dro you will get your
Rainbow body you'll get your Angel's
bunny okay and I've only brought this
quotation up because I want you to be
really
really clear that if you can see
emptiness directly it's a it's
intimately and automatically and can
even be suddenly related to becoming an
angel you see an reaching an angel's
body he's talking about higher level OFA
Arya okay and later on jetona says uh
look well I'll give I'll give it to
you uh then he discusses how that takes
place and he quotes from a scripture
called the the activities or something
like that it's a tantric scripture
somebody asked a question you know is it
possible instead of entering the Bardo
to become vajar you know or
vajani uh to enter that
body and then he gives a long
explanation of why that is possible and
why it will happen and this is bajar
talking to an know questioner okay in
this
Tantra then he says uh
GNA if you are able then to attain the
Angel's body the body of
light it's been stated that in that same
life you'll become a Buddha so like you
can't get the Miracle body the rainbow
body and not become a Buddha in the same
life so he's telling you if you want to
get to the rainbow body especially in
during the death process you must see
emptiness directly like you have to try
really hard do to see what they call the
Clear light of death and transform that
into a direct perception emptiness okay
and then you can get the rainbow body
and then if you get that you just become
de and that you become a Buddha in that
same life
but let's say you don't manage to
achieve rainbow body but you do manage
to perceive emptiness directly clear
light directly well then as theant
says okay and then he goes through that
quotation same
quotation uh where did that go
it is stated in
the that
mahay have
eliminated having to die through Karma
and cles okay Karma and mental
afflictions dear
Le then he goes through an interesting
explanation of why if you can see
directly emptiness and have B then by
the way you avoid all these other
problems like never having enough money
and stuff like that
okay let's see if there's anything else
here oh and then he says the main point
I wanted you to get that was this whole
process about getting an angel body
doesn't work unless you can see
emptiness directly just before that and
anybody who says different is wrong okay
so he's like saying you got to to
activate the the angel body you have to
see emptiness directly before that and
and and this particular section which is
from one of his commentaries on Tanta in
general uh he's saying that if you want
to get the at death you want to get the
Miracle body rainbow body you have to
try to practice and this is a practice
found in the baj that you know chuk okay
okay I thought I'd throw in another the
other the other place where jetona uses
this quotation
is from his commentary
onya which is in the kagu tradition
where the Maham mudra comes from and
then leads into a lot of like uh what
we're studying in the other class s
okay if you can achieve the fourth
level you'll experience the three
visions and you will see
directly because the gulama says because
the utar Tantra says and then he quotes
the same quotation then he says I like
this one and this is I think on your
homework
somewhere as
says if it's true as Lord MAA
says that people in the open
teachings uh who see emptiness directly
can get out of dying through Karma and
Claus
well means needless to say if you
practicing
tant then uh be no problem would it you
know if you saw Tinus directly and had
bodhicitta and we're practicing tant on
top of that well just forget it you know
and then he just leaves it like that
okay that's I like that quotation
anyway then there are a lot of more I'm
going to have in the reading a lot more
quotations about
um how it is that AAS can have to take
birth
again let me see if I can find
one here's a writer and it's uh again
it's from our
Monastery
um there somebody says um to him
uh there's an argument if if these
people who see emptiness directly have
to take seven more lifetimes then what
makes them do it you see what is there
that makes them do that and there's a
debate about it and he says
uh I'll give you two choices you know
the other guy the other guy seems to
want to say they must have some kind of
claas they got to have some kind of
mental afflictions otherwise they
wouldn't take breath you know so that's
where we're coming from somebody's
saying during those seven lifetimes they
must have some kind of mental
afflictions that are making them take
birth you don't take birth by accident
you know it's not like you just take
birth because of the what do you call it
the momentum you're on from billions of
past lives I mean after you seen
emptiness directly why do you still have
to take birth and and our guy gives the
other guy two choices he says the other
guy was sort of implying you need to
have a mental Affliction right he
says means any way any way they want
okay he says okay so you're saying that
these bod saaas they can't just take any
kind of birth they want through their
compassion and their prayer M right okay
are you telling me that is that what you
want mean to
say
and and that somehow uh there's some
kind of mental Affliction making them do
it right okay that's First Choice okay
they can't do it by compassion and
moonam there must be some kind of mental
fliction at work that's the first choice
I'll give you
because the other guy said
what there must be some mental
Affliction involved there okay then he
says I'll give you another Choice means
I'll give you another
Choice uh whether or not you agree that
this is a mental
Affliction Chapo said at the time when
you go into crossing the Borderland
between death and rebirth okay it's
called
CH everyone has this fear of of losing
their whole being okay like the thing
that makes you fight when somebody grabs
you on a roof and pushes you you know or
someone goes like that and and that
automatic fear it's what almost like ABI
nesa described in the yoga Su sometimes
that
[Music]
way then you get some horrible
attachment to this body and then that
throws you into another rebra you know
if you have that fear at the last moment
and you're like afraid that if you lose
this body you will disappear I will
disappear then that kind of fear is
called SE G sea in the Wheel of Life uh
attachment and then that throws you into
the next few breath so he says which way
you want it which way you want
it okay he's debating this other guy
says which way which way was it what was
the first choice
again they got some kind of mental
Affliction even though and they can't
take rebirth the they want through
compassion and prayer second
choice whether or not they have a mental
Affliction but they have this fear and
that's what throws them into the next
rebirth so I mean what we're debating
here is like we're already assuming you
see saw emptiness what do you do next
how can you cut those seven rebirths
short okay like we just went to the
tantric explanation right but now we
have this question this is essential
suppose you do see emptiness directly
you still want to spend some more
lifetimes you know maybe you could
identify what's throwing you into a
rebirth even after you see emptiness and
he says so here's a debate and he says
well there's two choices either you
can't take a bre birth where you
want or whether you call it a mental or
and and some mental Affliction throwing
you or whether you call it a mental
Affliction or not you've got some kind
of fear about me and that throws you
into your next okay which way do you
want it
the guy might pick the second way
why because it it gets out of a problem
it gets out of a problem
what that these that these bod saas who
have to take life seven more times and
he doesn't want to admit that they might
be able to do to Simply through their
own
compassion and by the way the compassion
thing is a little uh even to me I I
don't know if I buy it why I want to get
enlightened faster
well that and we know he has to take
seven more births we know we know he's
not a d he's not in our heart right he's
not in our heart I mean if you could
just see emptiness directly and then
immediately take any birth you
want it sounds like an arot to me it
sounds like a person who's like years
and years Beyond seeing emptiness
directly so what's the difference I mean
why do you have to go through the whole
path
of habituation where's that 500 years
where did it go is if the guy can just
take birth anywhere he wants then
where'd that 500 years go you know I
mean it I don't know if I buy it okay so
anyway he says uh then our guy doesn't
give the other guy a chance to answer
anyway he says uh either way it's
wrong because either way it would
contradict statements that these Arya
bodh satas have destroyed uh any being
forced to do things through Claus so
what our guy is saying is look whether
you call that fear a claa or not I call
it a claa it's a mental Affliction
okay and if your description was right
you know if
a had to take rebirth through any kind
of mental afflictions
sh means forget the idea that he's
helping others in a big way
he can't do what he wants to do for
himself you know he can't even do what
he wants to do what are you talking
acting for all living beings they can't
even keep their own rear end out of some
s out of some more births
okay now you got to debate that right
these are all like they're not all quite
matching each other they're all giving a
different angle I think if you spend
like a week or two reading it you could
you could probably reconcile them all
but I'm not
sure
uh I'm going to skip the next
one
uh yeah that's about the same I'll skip
the next one too
oh this is a good one this is by uh
Sarah Jetson Sarah Jetson is the author
of The Textbook series from the lower
College of
Sarah just kidding Sarah J okay and he
was the teacher of the author of our
textbooks kid
dead and there's a tradition that K I
mean according to us K dead outgrew as
teacher which is almost sort of a little
touchy subject right uh and according to
the SAS kodagi was sort of a Maverick
who just kind of wandered away from the
the party
line uh which seems to typify S
llamas
um by tradition but um
anyway however way you see it K CH
Papa somebody says look there is a
mental affliction
that arises in the mind of a bodh Arya
which makes them take rebirth in Sam
there is a mental F now that's a Kik
which means
what the other guy which means we we
don't buy it okay so this is the yeah
it's like the or the
okay also you're telling me there's a bu
Ayah who is forced to take rebirth out
of uh Karma and mental afflictions right
s uh he says teer I didn't say
that but but you started out with what
you started out with you said there's a
mental Affliction which makes him take
rebirth right and he says yeah so he's
taking rebirth because he's forced to
through mental afflictions right
no
okay you can't agree that he's forced to
take a rebirth through Karma and mental
afflictions because this this book says
something else which book
Tantra then he throws in this quotation
again this is I just want you to get the
feeling that this quotation has probably
been used more than any other quotation
from the enre Tantra because it's so
vital it's so important suppose I do see
emptiness directly well what's my status
how is it that I get an angel's body how
long will it really take okay does
tantric does tantric practice
help uh and then he's and they the our
guy figured that's enough he doesn't go
on you know that's enough but then he
throws in another
debate which
means there is too a mental Affliction
that makes the guy take birth
again because he's got a n
Dip N Dip is
[Music]
what Dippa is an obstacle okay Dipper
Dipper like we we have the capacity to
see every living being in the in the
universe you have the capacity to read
my mind at any given time you know
whether you are now I don't know but
everyone has that capacity in this room
and then there's this some block there's
a wall if you break through that wall
you can do all those things
like in principle you can perceive
everything happening in the universe in
principle anybody in this room if you
saw emptiness directly today
on you would see every living creature
in the universe in in one minute in one
in it but there's some kind of block you
see there's some kind of wall if you can
break it down that's called shid okay
shid means sha means it blocks you from
the ability to know all things at the
same time okay as opposed to aund which
is aonga which is what mental Affliction
obstacle which only prevents you from
what
achieving Nirvana okay so mental
Affliction obstacle just means something
that keep keeps you from achieving
nurana where you don't have to take
rebirth again at all for example and
shin is what prevents you from reaching
omnition omniscience okay okay so now
that you know that this guy says there
is a mental Affliction in the guy's mind
that makes him take one of those seven
births right because he's got a mental
Affliction
obstacle we say no he doesn't and he
says yeah he does cuz he has a
obacle right
say doesn't follow doesn't follow
doesn't necessarily follow you can have
a obstacle to your
omniscience but have gotten over your
obstacles to Nirvana right I mean we
know that but he makes a slip
luckily you bch and then the other guy
says he does too have an omniscience
obstacle and then he says something very
powerful because he still got the he's
still at the level where he has the seed
for
ignorance he's still at the level where
he has the seed for
ignorance is that a mental
Affliction no we talked about it before
today it's an energy it's an energy it's
not mental
okay anyway but the other guy is saying
saying does a me the seed for ignorance
is an obstacle to
omniscience and not to becoming an our
heart is that
true the question is do you get rid of
your seeds for your ignorance when you
become an our no because you're
om that's touchy what kind of ignorance
we talking about the one that sees the
things are self-existent you get over
that's the last thing you get over right
and the seeds for it or do you get rid
of the seeds for it what do you do
between the eth and 10th budhy SAA
levels long story okay anyway he seems
to be saying that this seed represents
the thing that blocks you from reaching
buddhahood omnicient obstacle okay the
seed not the ignorance itself ignorance
itself is already gone
okay then
therefore he says according to me this
guy has a mental Affliction that's going
to make him take birth
again but he's not taking birth to the
power of mental
afflictions supports me supports me
okay and then anyway the bottom line is
that the author from Sarah
J says that what if we treat
the energies in that bodh
mind as obstacles to
omniscience uh you know the energies for
ignorance the seeds for ignorance in
that body selfish mind what if we treat
them as obstacles to
omniscience
okay would they still take
birth rebirth I he's trying to say let's
classify them as something that's not
mental
Affliction but that still make them take
birth does that help us with our
problems
today what's utar Tantra say he's not
going to take birth again because they
don't they don't have it so they don't
have it meaning
what they don't have mental afflictions
and Karma so they're not going to take
rebirth now Sarah J guy is saying what
if we classify those seeds that make him
take birth again as not mental
Affliction obstacles but on
obstacles then is he still taking
rebirth yeah yeah because we know he has
to be because he's
a and seven
timer he's a seven timer and then can we
say he doesn't have mental
afflictions yes yeah we got out of it
that's a sah J okay now I'm not saying
it's right or wrong you got a che on it
but you get the point he's saying UT
tant is Right seven life is right taking
rebirth is right being truth of
suffering is right not being some is
right not being forced by Karma clist to
take rebirth is right but having to take
rebirth is right through something
mental Affliction sort of thing which
means the obstacle to omniscience which
is the seeds of the of the ignorance
okay so now you see how different
authors over hundreds of years are
shooting guns at each you know they're
like how about if we do it this way can
we does that
does that what do you call it reconcile
reconcile all these all these ideas okay
so so think about it think about it I
think it's just a classification trick
anyway uh but not necessarily wrong I
don't
[Music]
know and there's a couple more from
Serge but we don't need those uh
uh just
kidding here's a little thing I threw in
towards the end I think this is maybe
the last thing let me check yeah this is
the last thing I just threw this in at
the end for fun
okay this is from a l room text it's a
commentary to a l room that was written
by the first pension llama whose name is
loan chuki gansen and people confuse him
with Sarah Jetson Chui Genson who's the
textbook author from Sarah J so people
say Chuy Genson you have to say which
chy ganssen and you say Sarah Json Chi
Johansson oh the Sarah textbook writer
or they say pin Lon Chi johanssen and
then then it means the pension llama but
anyway we're talking about pension llama
he wrote A L room called the the easy
way the E like the short almost like the
easy the easy path okay uh Dam I don't
know if it's been translated yet anybody
know if it hasn't been I think it'd be
cool to do it for the first year of the
tantric series cuz I have a connect I
like penin losan gon he was a great
writer and a great
poet yeah yeah I don't know if anyone's
translated it's not very long and it'd
be a great L rim for us to do as the
first year of the tantrick series so
we'll either do that or the fifths I
don't know whatever is available by then
or you know whichever this one is kind
of to me is there's a very I have a
connection with it anyway he says
uh he says really if you think about it
people shouldn't get stuck in Middle
capacity middle level capacity meaning
what wanting to abandon cic existence to
end one's suffering yeah okay out of you
know n little capacity medium capacity
big capacity Lum right what they call it
Greater scope lesser scope medium scope
okay something fancy like that
R of all the people in history who are
watching out for their own rear end
okay something like
that the best the very
best means uh who is that I think it's
shra and modal kipu
modana these two great Disciples of Lord
Buddha they were great disciples in
which turning of the
wheel the second could be heart yeah I
guess you could say the
heart yeah that but anyway they're known
for having been there at the first one
mostly and they're known as having been
Terin those two
guys yeah they're known I think it's
those two I don't think it's a nand I
think it's mipu and sharu anyway they're
known as being tadan usually he says the
best of the people who weren't bodis
satas yet had to be those two okay
D they spent their whole lives trying to
achieve their own
goals and not only did they not help to
achieve others goals they didn't get
their own okay like he's putting them
down okay in Islam room
why they had an opportunity to view the
hell
reals there was some kind of controversy
involving a non- Buddhist teacher and
some letter he wrote to his disciples or
something anyway d
as a result of this
conversation got
punched
okay and he and he tied up his feet and
legs
uh I'm sorry he he he crushed his feet
and arms he crushed his arms and legs
like you would a a house of reads
remember that and he died M died uh
whereas if he had been a
bodh and if he had seen the emptiness
directly he never would have had any of
these
problems okay uh because people seen
emptiness directly and who are just
don't get these problems because utar
Tantra says all right so now you see how
this quotation is being used Us by many
many different people and it's you know
it's just a short class not really but I
it's just
a I just want you to get the feeling for
how Aya has has infiltrated all of
Tibetan Buddhism you see from many from
tanter gangle from L mangle from
Perfection of wisdom mangle almost
anything you read has RAR tant in it
whether you know it or not so here he's
using it for a different reason he's
using the quotation for a different
reason then he
says therefore if you're going to be a
good teacher for other people get them
right into talking about emptiness and
Karma okay get them right into talking
about empty if you're going to not waste
people's time get them right into
emptiness and Karma I like that and then
he quotes POA who's a famous kadampa uh
who said the same thing okay says don't
waste people's time don't fool around
don't monkey around get them straight
into Karma and emptiness get them to
bodh sa Arya right uh so that's all I'm
going to do on that I think especially
it'd be nice for you to review the the
statements about tantri the tantric part
and um how you can use Clear
light uh to achieve the same thing that
a on a tanter level tantric path that
someone using the ACI courses went on a
Sut CL the courses so far on sopath okay
so really the 18 courses that are coming
up next fall are for uh are for getting
to the second kind of
Arya okay who can use tantric practices
uh to shorten the time okay to get to
the same thing okay we'll stop there all
right uh we'll do prayers
she
[Music]
we're going to hit in August uh during
those three classes we'll hit Rick come
which is what Buddha nature Buddha
nature it's the guts of the utar Tantra
I mean this is very heavy part of utar
Tantra but really the heaviest part is
Buddha nature the the main subject in
there is Buddha nature and
I thought we would go over some of the
uh views of emptiness held by other
schools in Tibet like specifically
shenton which is uh one kagu approach to
emptiness which is which is wrong but
which is useful to study I think and and
I think by the time you get through with
that you'll know more about shenton than
the
shentong uh and that's very useful for
being able to talk to people you know
people get you know what do you call it
now they get like uh that comes with it
people say like I believe in shendong
you know and not what not empty I don't
believe that Emptiness is a lack of
something and you're
like uh well then what is shentong and
they said well I don't know but I heard
you know and and then you know you got
to be able to say well what you believe
is this this this and this you know and
here's the scriptures of your own that's
what we do in debate you study J Boon
and gandan scriptures you know and then
they start spouting something you say oh
you got that from son all right they say
yeah yeah that's what we believe I say
yeah but even according to that
scripture you can't accept it you know
and then they're like oh yeah you know
and then I mean in the monastery you
debate one very important method is to
really learn the system that the other
people hold like if you're going to be a
if you say I hold Maj Mika you know I
believe in maim Mika then you say well
why don't you believe in myoli and they
say well cuz myol is lower than my you
know and you say well why you know and
they say well I don't know but I hold
Maj Mika you know and then if you're
really going to do be a good maim mik
you got to know M only well you know and
you say well here's why mind only here's
the points on which M only differs from
maim you know so what I thought to do is
we'll do a we'll we'll do a similar
thing as we did today on shenton from
many different scriptures and we'll
throw in shentong from some from some of
the classic kagu sources that present it
and then we'll just thrash it out you
know we'll thrash it out we'll see both
sides like that and then that carries
over into Buddha nature the that idea of
emptiness is responsible for their view
on Buddha nature which we've read in San
this we're studying a very beautiful
scripture by one of the early kapas
which is very good and powerful but I
thought we'd throw that in there also
and you can get from the horse's mouth
you can get this idea about
Buddha nature that we don't agree with
but which is a very beautiful
presentation and most importantly
what no useful it's useful it's useful
like you got to have all these tools in
your toolbox you know there might come a
day when you run into a student who's
just got to hear that one you know and
you teach it to them you know you don't
mention the the the real idea of ESS you
go straight to oh yeah there is a little
buddha inside of you and you know like I
was at the prison yesterday and you just
see the level the people that are there
and then you have to shift you have to
do Tong immediately and so you got to
have in your toolbox everybody's idea
about emptiness and it's funny you know
you might or you might like I'm going to
a Yoga Center uh This Big Yoga Center
you know and so I presented uh yoga
Sutra way or I presented hat yoga padaka
way or I don't jump right into nag or
chanuk because they don't believe in
that so you you learn yoga sura well you
learn and and then you present it that
way and then you when they grasp it then
you bring them up right that was the
point of the utar Tantra itself right
the first three books were
what mine only but he said they you had
to have them for certain people to get
them up to to Ma so so we'll do a whole
everybody's idea about emptiness and
buha nature and then you'll be well
loaded by the time by by the time of
October but you got to look over this
stuff now also I'll send readings to La
after my vacation but before I get back
so um you know you'll have those
okay yeah yes yeah you can email them
okay yeah we love you very much of
everyone your teachings are amazing
please come back oh yeah continue no I
much rather be here than anywhere else I
this is the place to I'm at the place in
my life and I think those of you who are
over 40 you should start thinking that
way too where you know you got to be in
a place where you can do long deep
Retreats and
concentrate so I'm happy I think that's
the right place to be right now okay and
the tempting courses are being held here
so he